The extraordinary true story of Solomon Northup.
12 Years a Slave is a drama, history film directed by Steve McQueen.
In the pre-Civil War United States, Solomon Northup, a free black man
from upstate New York, is abducted and sold into slavery.
Facing cruelty as well as unexpected kindnesses Solomon struggles
not only to stay alive, but to retain his dignity.
In the twelfth year of his unforgettable odyssey, Solomon’s chance meeting
with a Canadian abolitionist will forever alter his life.
Solomon Northup, played by Chiwetel Ejiofor.
Edwin Epps, played by Michael Fassbender.
Patsey, played by Lupita Nyong'o.
William Ford, played by Benedict Cumberbatch.
John Tibeats, played by Paul Dano.
Mary Epps, played by Sarah Paulson.
12 Years a Slave is a 2013 biographical historical drama film directed by Steve McQueen from a screenplay by John Ridley, based on  the
1853 slave memoir Twelve Years a Slave by Solomon Northup, an American of mixed race, who was kidnapped from Washington, D.C.
by two conmen in 1841 and sold into slavery.
He was put to work on plantations in the state of
Louisiana for 12 years before being released.
The first scholarly edition of David Wilson's version of Northup's story
was co-edited in 1968 by Sue Eakin and Joseph Logsdon.
In the film, Chiwetel Ejiofor stars as Solomon Northup.
Supporting roles are portrayed by Michael Fassbender, Benedict Cumberbatch, Paul Dano, Garret Dillahunt, Paul Giamatti, Scoot
McNairy, Lupita Nyong'o, Adepero Oduye, Sarah Paulson, Brad Pitt, Michael Kenneth Williams, and Alfre Woodard.
Principal photography took place in New Orleans,
Louisiana, from June 27 to August 13, 2012.
The locations used were four historic antebellum plantations:
Felicity, Bocage, Destrehan, and Magnolia.
Of the four, Magnolia is nearest to the actual
plantation where Northup was held.
12 Years a Slave received widespread critical acclaim and was named the
best film of 2013 by several media outlets and critics.
It earned over $187 million on a production budget of $22 million.
The film received nine Academy Award nominations, winning for Best Picture, Best
Adapted Screenplay for Ridley, and Best Supporting Actress for Nyong'o.
The Best Picture win made McQueen the first black British producer to ever receive the
award and the first black British director of a Best Picture winner.
The film was awarded the Golden Globe Award for Best Motion Picture – Drama, and the British Academy of Film and
Television Arts recognized it with the BAFTA Awards for Best Film and Best Actor for Ejiofor.
Since its release, the film has been cited as among the best of the 2010s, the 21st century, and of all time, with it being named the 44th greatest film since
2000 in a BBC poll of 177 critics in 2016 and the 51st best film of the 21st century in a New York Times poll of over 500 filmmakers in 2025.
In 2023, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically or aesthetically
significant", making it the ninth film designated in its first year of eligibility, the 49th Best Picture Academy Award winner and the most recently released film to be selected.
The film explores themes of slavery, plantation, based on memoir
or autobiography, violin player, physical abuse.
The tone is emotional.